Obi-Wan's holding me back he doesn't
understand my
power Anakin Anakin syndrome you whiny
whiny
Anakin um what is Anakin Anakin syndrome
is the name that I came up with
for really smart
people who become so full of hubris and
and confidence in themselves that they
end up thinking everything is holding
them back and if you're in technology
you are probably acquainted with
somebody from this it's one thing to be
confident and have hubris it's one and
and you know and say oh I got new
information I was wrong like oh I don't
know somebody just asked me why I don't
like wsl2 because I used to say it was
the best thing best Linux distribution
ever made and now I'm like if you use it
you're an idiot speaking to myself who
used it for a long time changing your
mind is is not Anakin syndrome Anakin
syndrome is when you get so good at
something that you start to think you're
better than everybody else and I've
talked about this before in another
video but I'm going to tell the story
again really quickly here's how the
story goes um there was a guy who I
taught um and he mentored some time ago
and he got really good he was kind of
small and then he got kind of big and um
you know he was he was good at what he
was doing and everything but then he got
so full of himself that he started
saying oh you know you don't understand
you're dumb and then he started thinking
he was better than the
teacher um and become a Sith Lords right
only a Sith Lord deals in absolutes
right when I I use absolutes all the
time but still um you know the idea of
Anakin syndrome is that um by the way
that whole Sith Lord thing it's [__]
it's tot [__] sometimes there are
things that are AB 1+ 1 equals 2 it's an
absolute I'm not a Seth Sith Lord I'm a
Kindergarten kid who knows how to do
math so that's George Lucas just being
an idiot it's totally stupid we're not
going to go there okay um there are
absolutes in the world there absolutely
are absolutes in the world um there is
one best way to do many many things
that's actually a very important
principle that we'll talk about in
another video so anyway this guy thought
he knew everything and to take him aside
and say hey
um you got to stop countering me in the
classroom it's not okay even if you
disagree we can talk about it outside of
the classroom and he's like well okay
whatever you know and he you could tell
that he just felt out of you know he
felt like he knew more than everybody
and and then he started posting you know
lessons as his own uh and claiming you
know basically having everybody tell him
how cool he was and awesome I'm like
dude okay that's fine to do that but you
you know you should give credit where
credit is due and I'm not asking for
credit I'm saying that you should not be
pumping up perception that you're better
and and then it kind of dawned on me
that he didn't even realize that that
was happening and that is going to lead
us to the other part of this Anakin
syndrome really is something called the
Dunning Krueger effect um so let's go
ahead and do research for this this is
something we can actually search for
what is the
Dunning uh
Krueger effect all right you going go
search on the internet the dun and krer
effect is a cognitive bias in which
people are with limited competence in a
particular domain overestimate their
abilities it was first described by
Justin Krueger and David Dunning in
1999 some uh researchers also include
the opposite effect for high performers
their their tendency to underestimate
their skills which we also talked about
earlier that is impostor syndrome so dun
and Krueger is you know when you think
you are better than you are and you
don't know that in fact if you want a
visual pneumonic device uh to to to to
latch on to I I never forget the scene
where Anakin doesn't have
legs I mean you know and he's like
burning and he's you know oh sorry
spoiler alert and
um and Obi want to standing above him
he's like he's like I hate you Anakin's
like I hate you and oban's like I loved
you Anakin another horrible horrible
writing but you know still you know he's
like I loved you I treated you like a
son anak he's like my hat well you know
what that is that's what happens when
when you know Anakin syndrome fails it's
the end result of Anakin syndrome and
and by the way the scene right before
that is very very instructive so Anakin
is there he thinks he is all that man
he's full of Anakin syndrome he's got
dun and Krueger effect he thinks that
he's better than everything else he
thinks he's better than his leader his
master and it it's goes beyond arrogance
right and Obi-Wan's like Anakin I have
The High Ground I mean come on I taught
you better than that I got The High
Ground goes don't do it Anakin just
don't do it just just you know put your
sword your lightsaber down and just call
it a day
nope nope not Anakin full of Dunning
Krueger effect he tries to show that
he's better than his master and he
actually was better than his master a
lot of things but when it come down to
practical wisdom a lot of times his
master in that case is like cut his legs
off and frankly sometimes the only way
if you're an educator sometimes the only
way you can deal with somebody who's
really really good who hasn't done that
is cut their legs off I'm not
metaphorically
speaking because they just will not get
it and by the way hopefully when you cut
their legs up you know eventually they
come around and like you were right
about me you were right about me Luke
when I beheaded all of those younglings
and now I am saved through the grace of
the
force yeah if you can tell I don't like
Star Wars at
all but it serves as a good pneumonic
device for this opposite of impostor
syndrome oh I can't do anything I suck
like I can do anything you can't stop me
it's a bad thing it's hubris out of
control and it is all over it is all
over just avoid it do the best you can
to try to help yourself avoid it and by
the way how can you protect yourself
from dun and Krueger
effect mostly you need accountability
Partners In Your Circle it could be your
wife who's ripping you down all time and
telling you that you're they they
support you but they also don't lie to
you right isn't that great it's great if
you have a spouse that's that way but it
doesn't necessarily have to be a spouse
it can be it can be a a recruiter it can
be your Mentor it can be somebody who's
in the industry um bottom line it just
means that you need to listen to them
and if you for some reason don't think
that your current Mentor knows what
they're talking about then seek another
opinion you know go go and ultimately
you are still in control but but I think
the big biggest thing to own here is
that you accept that you are going to
have cognitive biases you just are
there's no way any human can avoid them
uh unfortunately there are some humans
who deny that they have cognitive biases
and I think what I'm encouraging myself
and everyone to do here is to accept the
fact and reevaluate the fact that we
have unknown cognitive biases all the
time and one of the biggest ones is done
in crew especially among technologists